<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Jermain C. Kaminski</title>
    <link href="https://jermainkaminski.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://jermainkaminski.com" />
    <updated>2025-09-10T09:53:36+02:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Jermain Kaminski</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://jermainkaminski.com</id>

    <entry>
        <title>The Sistine Chapel Problem</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jermain Kaminski</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://jermainkaminski.com/what-good-will-hunting-can-teach-about-ai/"/>
        <id>https://jermainkaminski.com/what-good-will-hunting-can-teach-about-ai/</id>
        <media:content url="https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/Will20Hunting.jpg.webp" medium="image" />

        <updated>2025-09-08T21:50:03+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/Will20Hunting.jpg.webp" alt="" />
                    <p class="dropcap">In a time when Large Language Models (LLM) can write beautiful essays and solve hard problems in seconds, educators have to ask themselves a basic question: what is the most important thing about learning? The answer, which may surprise you, can be found in a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8GY3sO47YYo" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">park bench conversation from a 1997 movie</a> (video).</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/Will20Hunting.jpg.webp" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p class="dropcap">In a time when Large Language Models (LLM) can write beautiful essays and solve hard problems in seconds, educators have to ask themselves a basic question: what is the most important thing about learning? The answer, which may surprise you, can be found in a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8GY3sO47YYo" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">park bench conversation from a 1997 movie</a> (video).</p>

<p class="whitespace-normal break-words">When students use an LLM to complete an assignment or thesis, they receive what appears to be a perfect product: well-structured, grammatically correct, comprehensive and convincing. But this perfection masks an absence. The student hasn't wrestled with confused thoughts, hasn't experienced the frustration of arguments in the literature that won't cohere, hasn't felt the satisfaction of finally understanding something that once seemed impenetrable. Learning has always been imperfect by design. The crossed-out sentences, the failed analogies, the flash of genuine insight amid confusion—these are not bugs in the educational system but features. They represent understanding being forged rather than downloaded, knowledge earned rather than accessed.</p>
<p class="whitespace-normal break-words">This tension between information and experience, between knowing about something and knowing it, predates artificial intelligence. But what if the greatest threat to education isn't that students work with AI, but that they'll never develop the capacity for original thought? How will we cultivate the next generation of researchers and practitioners if they never experience the disorientation of not knowing? When every difficult question yields an instant, polished answer, who will develop the intellectual muscle to tackle problems that have no solutions yet?</p>
<p>In my view, a more than twenty-year-old film about an intellectually talented janitor from South Boston offers an unexpected lens for understanding what we're about to lose.</p>
<h2 class="text-xl font-bold text-text-100 mt-1 -mb-0.5">What It Smells Like in the Sistine Chapel</h2>
<p class="whitespace-normal break-words">In <em>Good Will Hunting</em>, psychologist Sean Maguire (Robin Williams) confronts Will Hunting (Matt Damon), a brilliant but emotionally guarded young man who can recite facts about virtually anything, with a profound challenge about the nature of knowledge:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="whitespace-normal break-words">"If I asked you about art, you'd probably give me the skinny on every art book ever written. Michelangelo, you know a lot about him. Life's work, political aspirations, him and the pope, sexual orientations, the whole works, right? But I'll bet you can't tell me what it smells like in the Sistine Chapel. You've never actually stood there and looked up at that beautiful ceiling."</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="whitespace-normal break-words">This scene makes clear a difference that has become very important in our time. Large Language Models, like Will in a the famous Harvard bar scene at the inception of the plot, can provide the surface on any topic: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LMD2vUErcYU" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">dates, facts, connections, analysis</a>. They can tell you about Michelangelo's techniques, the chapel's dimensions, the theological symbolism of each panel. But they cannot tell you what it smells like in that sacred space, the trace of incense from morning mass, how your neck aches from craning upward, or the short hush that falls over tourists as they enter the chapel. They do did not experience the occasional gasp when someone spots Adam's finger. They cannot convey how small you feel standing beneath the human-made frescoes.</p>
<h2 class="text-xl font-bold text-text-100 mt-1 -mb-0.5"><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/pierre-goiffon-aR_COwiGzP0-unsplash.jpg" alt="" width="1920" height="1280" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" srcset="https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/responsive/pierre-goiffon-aR_COwiGzP0-unsplash-xs.webp 300w ,https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/responsive/pierre-goiffon-aR_COwiGzP0-unsplash-sm.webp 480w ,https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/responsive/pierre-goiffon-aR_COwiGzP0-unsplash-md.webp 768w ,https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/responsive/pierre-goiffon-aR_COwiGzP0-unsplash-xl.webp 1200w ,https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/responsive/pierre-goiffon-aR_COwiGzP0-unsplash-xxl.webp 1600w ,https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/responsive/pierre-goiffon-aR_COwiGzP0-unsplash-xxxl.webp 2560w"></figure></h2>
<h2 class="text-xl font-bold text-text-100 mt-1 -mb-0.5">The "How" Versus the "Why"</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0896627317305093" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Despite large advances in neuroscience-inspired machine learning</a>, and evolutionary algorithms that taught computers to fail via <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0893608022001150" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">reinforcement learning</a>, failure taught them optimization, not the weight of disappointment, not the frustration of learning. Philosophers call this the <em>explanatory gap </em>(Levine, 1983)<em>, or Dasein </em>(Heidegger, 1927);<em> </em>they process signals but never cross into sensation.</p>
<p class="whitespace-normal break-words">Without doubt, computers excel at the mechanics of knowledge: the <em>how</em>. They can demonstrate problem-solving steps, generate structurally sound arguments, and synthesize information from many databases it crawled or is able to access ad-hoc. This is undeniably valuable for education. Students can receive instant feedback, explore ideas at their own pace, and access personalized tutoring, complementing what we for instance do at Maastricht University in problem based learning (PBL).</p>
<p class="whitespace-normal break-words">Yet education, at its core, has always been about the <em>why</em>. Why does this mathematical proof matter? Why should we care about the fall of Rome? Why does this poem move us? Why do I control for collinearity with the Variance Inflation Factor (<a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/10944281231216381" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">or why should I not?</a>). These questions require not just information processing but understanding. The kind of insight that emerges from struggle, contemplation, and failure.</p>
<p>One of my undergraduate professors for economics and philosophy, <a href="https://priddat.de/biographie/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Birger Priddat</a>, once ended a lecture with a claim that followed me: "By the end of your studies, you should have read a stable of books at least taller than yourself. You need to <em>experience</em> it, you need to <em>doubt</em> it, at the risk of being wrong". When Sean challenges Will about the Sistine Chapel, Sean is making Priddat's point: there is knowledge you can access and knowledge you must undergo. The stack of books taller than yourself is not about the information contained within their pages, which any LLM could summarize in seconds. It's about becoming someone different by the time you reach the top: tired, changed, and carrying not just what you've read but who you've become through reading it.</p>
<p>We're all experiencing this shift in how research develops. Post-GPT, theses cite more sources than ever but engage less deeply. What one might calls stratospheric scholarship, flying at 30,000 feet above the actual methodological terrain and touching topics one at a time. With LLMs, literature reviews have become remarkably comprehensive. More sources, broader coverage, impressive bibliographies. Who could resist such an efficient research assistant? Yet something subtle is lost in this efficiency: the deep, sometimes frustrating engagement with a paper's methodology, sampling, the wrestling with its limitations, the slow dawning of what it really means in context. In thesis defenses, this trade-off becomes visible: students have genuinely worked hard, used the tools available to them, yet find themselves strangers to their own citations. It's not a failure of effort but a consequence of tools that make the wrong parts easy.</p>
<h2 class="text-xl font-bold text-text-100 mt-1 -mb-0.5">Your Move, Chief</h2>
<p>In the movie, Sean continues his challenge to Will:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You're an orphan right? You think I know the first thing about how hard your life has been, how you feel, who you are, because I read Oliver Twist?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here's another realisation: genuine knowledge is individualised and influenced by our individual experiences with other people. The bench scene serves as a reminder that transformative education is also relational, which is perhaps its most significant lesson. Sean's breakthrough with Will isn't the result of superior knowledge or clever reasoning. It comes from being vulnerable, from sharing his own grief over his wife's passing, and from having a real human connection. "Your move," he says, asking Will to engage authentically rather than simply reciting facts.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/1HfekqjcJN1HXe2zWWGaG8g2x.jpg" alt="" width="1242" height="666" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" srcset="https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/responsive/1HfekqjcJN1HXe2zWWGaG8g2x-xs.webp 300w ,https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/responsive/1HfekqjcJN1HXe2zWWGaG8g2x-sm.webp 480w ,https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/responsive/1HfekqjcJN1HXe2zWWGaG8g2x-md.webp 768w ,https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/responsive/1HfekqjcJN1HXe2zWWGaG8g2x-xl.webp 1200w ,https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/responsive/1HfekqjcJN1HXe2zWWGaG8g2x-xxl.webp 1600w ,https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/responsive/1HfekqjcJN1HXe2zWWGaG8g2x-xxxl.webp 2560w"></figure>
<p class="whitespace-normal break-words">This relational dimension, the classroom discussions where ideas spark and clash, the mentorship that shapes not just what we know but who we become, cannot be algorithmatically reproduced. Also from the educator's perspective, an LLM can provide feedback, but it cannot see the particular student before it, the thought vector one comes from, cannot recognize the moment when confusion shifts to comprehension, cannot share in the joy of discovery.</p>
<h2 class="text-xl font-bold text-text-100 mt-1 -mb-0.5">Desirable Difficulties</h2>
<p class="whitespace-normal break-words">The idea is not to banish LLMs from education. They are powerful tools that, used thoughtfully, can enhance learning. Students can use them to explore ideas, check understanding, and overcome barriers to entry in complex subjects. In my own entrepreneurship teaching, I encourage students to use text, image, and video generation methods to imagine future products and services. In causal inference, I employ LLM to look for <a href="https://github.com/py-why/pywhyllm" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">potential confounders or omitted variables</a>. That being said, we must resist the temptation to mistake the tool, a cognitive limb, for the purpose.</p>
<p class="whitespace-normal break-words">The key lies in preserving what cognitive scientists call <em>desirable difficulties: </em>the <em>productive</em> <em>friction</em> that actually enables learning. Possibly through <a href="https://fortune.com/2025/09/07/stanford-professor-jure-leskovec-hand-written-graded-tests-ai/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">written exams</a>, to take a recent case in point from Jure Leskovec, Professor for Computer Science at Stanford University, one of the epicenters of LLM research. When LLMs remove all resistance from the educational process, they may inadvertently remove the very mechanisms through which understanding develops. It's the cognitive equivalent of using a GPS for every journey: efficient, certainly, but we never develop our own sense of direction. The job market might pay a premium for that very skill of being able to read a map.</p>
<p class="whitespace-normal break-words">Now, how might we design friction back into AI-assisted learning? Most recently, syllabi suggest students could use LLMs to explore multiple perspectives on a topic but be required to defend their own synthesis without algorithmic help. They might employ AI to generate counterarguments to their thesis, forcing them to strengthen their reasoning. </p>
<p class="whitespace-normal break-words">However, the most promising educational applications of AI might be those that increase rather than decrease meaningful cognitive friction, by design. Imagine an LLM that refuses to answer directly but instead guides students through productive confusion, or one that generates problems tailored to sit just beyond a student's current ability, in what <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zone_of_proximal_development" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Vygotsky</a> called the zone of <em>proximal development</em>. Or they could use LLMs as sophisticated tutors that ask Socratic questions, rather than answers, maintaining the struggle that builds intellectual muscle.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/image.png" alt="" width="2001" height="1334" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" srcset="https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/responsive/image-xs.webp 300w ,https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/responsive/image-sm.webp 480w ,https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/responsive/image-md.webp 768w ,https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/responsive/image-xl.webp 1200w ,https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/responsive/image-xxl.webp 1600w ,https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/19/responsive/image-xxxl.webp 2560w"></figure>
<p>A recent <a href="https://time.com/7295195/ai-chatgpt-google-learning-school/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MIT study</a> that went viral claimed to show measurable IQ drops in 18-39 year old who regularly used GPT for problem-solving tasks, sparking a debate about AI's cognitive impacts. While the study's methodology and sample size invite legitimate skepticism, its central concern reflects well-established neuroscience. Research on neuroplasticity demonstrates that effortful learning, or what <a href="https://static1.squarespace.com/static/631f3333434573769b6da366/t/64513774777e291579ff8078/1683044212516/2019.01.09+Bjork.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Bjork &amp; Bjork (2011)</a> term <em>desirable difficulties, </em>creates more robust neural pathways than passive reception of information. When we struggle with a problem, our brains form denser synaptic connections through a process neuroscientists call <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Long-term_potentiation" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">long-term potentiation</a>. Problem-solving engages deeper memory consolidation in the hippocampus and prefrontal cortex. <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0010945213001391" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">fMRI studies</a> show markedly different brain activation patterns when individuals visually engage, for instance via <a href="https://cpb-us-w2.wpmucdn.com/sites.udel.edu/dist/6/132/files/2010/11/Psychological-Science-2014-Mueller-0956797614524581-1u0h0yu.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">handwriting</a>. </p>
<h2 class="text-xl font-bold text-text-100 mt-1 -mb-0.5">The Experience Game</h2>
<p class="whitespace-normal break-words">As we integrate artificial intelligence into our educational systems, we might recall that moment on the bench when Sean tells Will about his late wife: "<em>Those are the things I miss the most. The little idiosyncrasies that only I know about. That's what made her my wife.</em>" His point isn't about love, it's about the irreplaceable nature of lived experience. Those idiosyncrasies couldn't be summarized or transferred; they had to be discovered through years of attention, presence, and possibly <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/joms.12890" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">serendipity</a>. Education is often built on these irreplaceable, untransferable moments of human understanding.</p>
<p>Ironically, while modern LLMs might pass Turing's <a href="https://academic.oup.com/mind/article-abstract/LIX/236/433/986238" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>Imitation Game</em></a> through text, they fail what we might call the 'Sistine Chapel Test', not whether they can describe experience convincingly, but whether they've had experience at all. Turing proposed to consider the question, "<em>Can machines think?</em>." Sean asks us whether knowledge without experience is knowledge at all.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Welkom! 🇳🇱 </title>
        <author>
            <name>Jermain Kaminski</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://jermainkaminski.com/here-goes-a-new-post/"/>
        <id>https://jermainkaminski.com/here-goes-a-new-post/</id>
        <media:content url="https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/12/Jermain-Kaminski-1-md.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="News"/>

        <updated>2025-06-08T19:16:17+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/12/Jermain-Kaminski-1-md.jpg" alt="Jermain Kaminski" />
                    <p>I am an Assistant Professor of Entrepreneurship and Innovation (with tenure) at the School of Business and Economics at Maastricht University. My <a href="https://jermainkaminski.com/research/">research</a> specializes on entrepreneurship, strategy, and causal machine learning, with a focus on how data-driven methods can improve decision-making and innovation. I'm a co-founder of the <a href="https://causalscience.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Causal Data Science Meeting</a>.</p>
<p class="">My work has been published in academic journals across innovation studies and computer science, such as the <em>Journal of Business Venturing, Journal of Product Innovation Management, ACM CHI conference on Human Factors in Computing, or IEEE Transactions on Engineering Management,</em> and received coverage in media outlets such as <em>Harvard Business Review</em> or <em>Poets &amp; Quants</em>.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/12/Jermain-Kaminski-1-md.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Jermain Kaminski" /></p>
                <p>I am an Assistant Professor of Entrepreneurship and Innovation (with tenure) at the School of Business and Economics at Maastricht University. My <a href="https://jermainkaminski.com/research/">research</a> specializes on entrepreneurship, strategy, and causal machine learning, with a focus on how data-driven methods can improve decision-making and innovation. I'm a co-founder of the <a href="https://causalscience.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Causal Data Science Meeting</a>.</p>
<p class="">My work has been published in academic journals across innovation studies and computer science, such as the <em>Journal of Business Venturing, Journal of Product Innovation Management, ACM CHI conference on Human Factors in Computing, or IEEE Transactions on Engineering Management,</em> and received coverage in media outlets such as <em>Harvard Business Review</em> or <em>Poets &amp; Quants</em>.</p>

<p>Over the past years, I bridged practical technical expertise with training in economics. I obtained my PhD in 2019 from <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20211001230253/https://time.rwth-aachen.de/">RWTH Aachen University</a> (Commission: Christian Hopp, Frank Piller, Oliver Salge). During my graduate studies and PhD, I was a visiting researcher at the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20211001230253/https://cci.mit.edu/">MIT Center for Collective Intelligence</a> at the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20211001230253/https://mitsloan.mit.edu/">MIT Sloan School of Management</a> (Thomas Malone &amp; Peter Gloor) and Collective Learning Group at the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20211001230253/https://media.mit.edu/">MIT Media Lab</a> (César Hidalgo). I studied at <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20211001230253/https://www.uni-wh.de/en/uwh-international/start/">Witten/Herdecke University</a>, Germany, and was a visiting student at the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20211001230253/https://mit.edu/">Massachusetts Institute of Technology</a>, USA. I am a co-founder of the startup <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20211001230253/https://moviegalaxies.com/">MovieGalaxies</a>, providing open source network data on <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20211001230253/https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataset.xhtml?persistentId=doi:10.7910/DVN/T4HBA3">Harvard DataVerse</a>. In 2014-2015, I worked in a research project on data analytics in soccer for a Bundesliga club, specializing on complexity in passing networks. I further gained experienced working at central marketing at Dr. Ing. h.c. F. Porsche AG, executive consulting with <a href="https://www.drgeorgfischer.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Dr. Georg Th. Fischer</a>, and working in smaller consulting projects such as the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SpaceLiner" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">German Space Liner</a> (German Aerospace Center).</p>
<p>Together with co-authors, I have published on using <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20211001230253/https://doi.org/10.1007/s11187-019-00218-w">machine leaning to predict outcomes in crowdfunding with text, speech, and video information</a>, on <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20211001230253/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.techfore.2018.11.015">predicting venture capital investments with crowdfunding data</a>, on <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20211001230253/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbusvent.2020.106021">experimental studies of psychological distance in product crowdfunding</a>, and on <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20211001230253/https://hbr.org/2018/04/what-40-years-of-research-reveals-about-the-difference-between-disruptive-and-radical-innovation">topic models of disruptive innovation research</a>.  My research with colleagues is cited in official reports by the Organisation for <em>Economic Co-operation and Development</em> (OECD) and the Publications Office of the European Union, particularly within the Joint Research Centre of the <em>European Commission</em>.</p>
<p>I have been awarded the <em>Best Teacher </em>Award at my faculty and was nominated for the Wynand Wijnen Education Prize on university level. My PhD thesis (summa cum laude) received the <em>Borchers Badge</em> at RWTH Aachen. I was a Fellow of the <em>Royal Society of Arts</em> and <em>Marshall Memorial Fellow</em> at the Marshall Fund of the United States. In 2012 I was happy to be a participant in the first <em>Y Combinator Startup School</em> and winning a <em>Best Practice Paper</em> Award at Stanford Medicine X. My initiative Nachhaltigkeistspreis.de was acquired by an initiative of the German Federal Government. Among my early adventures: serving as a UEFA Champions League 2004 Junior Journalist, where Jürgen Klinsmann and Eusébio presented me and three others with the award. Pure luck? Probably. Unforgettable? Absolutely.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Causal Data Science Meeting</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jermain Kaminski</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://jermainkaminski.com/test-6/"/>
        <id>https://jermainkaminski.com/test-6/</id>
        <media:content url="https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/9/um-tapijn-202010-005_2-2.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="News"/>

        <updated>2024-09-16T10:25:00+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/9/um-tapijn-202010-005_2-2.jpg" alt="" />
                    <p>We’re excited to open submissions for the Causal Data Science Meeting 2025, bringing together researchers and practitioners to explore how causality is shaping the future of machine learning and AI.<br><br>Keynote: We’re honored to welcome Prof. <a href="https://www.som.lmu.de/en/faculty/people-overview/contact-page/stefan-feuerriegel-840c1071.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Stefan Feuerriegel</a> as our 2025 keynote speaker! He heads the Institute of Artificial Intelligence in Management and holds dual appointments at LMU Munich’s School of Management and the Faculty of Mathematics, Informatics, and Statistics. His research on causal ML and AI in decision-making will offer valuable insights for the community.</p>
<p>Event: Nov 12–13, 2025 (Virtual)<br>Submission Deadline: Sept 30, 2025</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/9/um-tapijn-202010-005_2-2.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>We’re excited to open submissions for the Causal Data Science Meeting 2025, bringing together researchers and practitioners to explore how causality is shaping the future of machine learning and AI.<br><br>Keynote: We’re honored to welcome Prof. <a href="https://www.som.lmu.de/en/faculty/people-overview/contact-page/stefan-feuerriegel-840c1071.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Stefan Feuerriegel</a> as our 2025 keynote speaker! He heads the Institute of Artificial Intelligence in Management and holds dual appointments at LMU Munich’s School of Management and the Faculty of Mathematics, Informatics, and Statistics. His research on causal ML and AI in decision-making will offer valuable insights for the community.</p>
<p>Event: Nov 12–13, 2025 (Virtual)<br>Submission Deadline: Sept 30, 2025</p>

<p>Causality has long been an important topic in various disciplines including computer science, economics, the social sciences, epidemiology, and philosophy. In recent years, interest has also grown in the business sector with both experimental (such as A/B testing, reinforcement learning, business experimentation) and observational causal inference methods (such causal discovery, root-cause analysis, quasi-experimental methods) being increasingly applied by practitioners. <br><br>Ever since its launch, the Causal Data Science Meeting has been at the forefront of this development, connecting a global audience of causality experts from academia and industry. We are excited to announce this year's Causal Data Science Meeting, which will take place as a two-day virtual conference on <em>November 12-13, 2025</em>. The event will focus on the newest methodological advances, practical aspects, and organizational challenges related to the adoption of causal machine learning tools. It will feature invited talks and presentations of accepted proposals.‍<br>‍<br><strong>Workshop Date:</strong><br>November 12–13<br><strong>Submission Deadline:</strong><br>September 30<br><strong>Acceptance Notification:<br></strong>October 7<br><br>Please submit your presentation proposal, extended abstract or full paper to <a href="mailto:submission@causalscience.org?subject=Submission%3A%20CDSM2025"><strong>submission@causalscience.org</strong></a><br><br>The meeting is organized as a workshop for the purpose of facilitating discussion and disseminating ideas. No conference proceedings of accepted presentations will be published. If you want to register as a participant, without presenting, please click <a href="https://forms.gle/SfZBdkXc44tvqEas9" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here</a>.<a href="https://forms.gle/5URSgebmn61E4zwy6" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><br>‍</strong></a><br>If your organization would like to sponsor the event, please contact us at <strong>contact@causalscience.org</strong>.</p>
<hr>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/9/Mail-Yellow.jpg" alt="Causal Data Science Meeting 2025" width="1200" height="1200" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" srcset="https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/9/responsive/Mail-Yellow-xs.webp 300w ,https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/9/responsive/Mail-Yellow-sm.webp 480w ,https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/9/responsive/Mail-Yellow-md.webp 768w ,https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/9/responsive/Mail-Yellow-xl.webp 1200w ,https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/9/responsive/Mail-Yellow-xxl.webp 1600w ,https://jermainkaminski.com/media/posts/9/responsive/Mail-Yellow-xxxl.webp 2560w"></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
